Ben Roche: So I'm Ben, by the way.
بين روشيه : بالمناسبة إسمي بين
Homaro Cantu: And I'm Homaro.
هومارو كانتو : و أنا هوماروا
BR: And we're chefs. So when Moto
بين روشيه : نحن طُهاة , عندما إفتتحنا" موتو "
opened in 2004, people didn't really know
في عام 2004 , لم تكن الناس تعي
what to expect. A lot of people thought
الذي سوف نقدمه , العديد من الاشخاص
that it was a Japanese restaurant, and
ظنوا انه مطعم ياباني , ربما ..
maybe it was the name, maybe it was
بسبب الاسم , ربما بسبب الشعار
the logo, which was like a Japanese
الذي يبدو ..
character, but anyway, we had all these
كحرف ياباني .. ولكن بصورة عامة
requests for Japanese food, which is
كنا نتلقى العديد من طلبات الاطعمة اليابانية
really not what we did. And after about
والتي لم تكن لدينا في الأساس وبعد فترة
the ten thousandth request for a maki roll,
وبعد 10,000 طلب للفائف "الماكي"
we decided to give the people
قررنا أن نبدأ بإعداد
what they wanted. So this picture is
مايريدون .. ما ترونه في الصورة
an example of printed food, and this was
وهو مثال عن " صور الأطعمة " و هذه كانت
the first foray into what we like to call
اول غزوة فيما يمكننا وصفه
flavor transformation. So this is all
بتحويل " النكهة " هذه كل
the ingredients, all the flavor of, you know,
المكونات .. كل النكهات
a standard maki roll, printed onto
الموجودة في لفائف الماكاي , مطبوعة
a little piece of paper.
على ورقة صغيرة
HC: So our diners started to get bored
هومارو كانتو : و من ثم بدأ الزبائن يضجرون
with this idea, and we decided to give them
من هذه الفكرة .. فقررنا
the same course twice, so here we actually
انا نعيد عليهم الدرس مرة أخرى .. فهاكم كما ترون
took an element from the maki roll and
عبارة عن عنصر من لفائف " الماكاي "
and took a picture of a dish and then
وصورة للطبق .. و من ثم
basically served that picture with the dish.
تقديم الطبق مع الصورة
So this dish in particular is basically
وهذا الطبق بالتحديد هو
champagne with seafood.
شمبانيا و طعام بحري
The champagne grapes that you see are
ان عنب الشمبانيا التي ترونها هنا
actually carbonated grapes. A little bit of
هي عبارة عن حبات عنب غازية ومع الطعام البحري
seafood and some crème fraiche and the
ونكهة الكريمة الذاكية والصورة
picture actually tastes exactly like the dish. (Laughter)
التي تبدو نكهتها تماما كما الصحن نحصل على طبق مميز ( ضحك )
BR: But it's not all just edible pictures.
بين روشيه : لم نقف عن الصور القابلة للأكل
We decided to do something
لقد قررنا ان نقوم بشيء مختلف
a little bit different and transform flavors
وأن نقوم بتحويل للنكهات
that were very familiar -- so in this case,
التي كانت شائعة جداً .. في هذه الحالة
we have carrot cake.
لدينا فطيرة الجزر
So we take a carrot cake, put it
اخذنا فطيرة الجزر
in a blender, and we have kind of like
ووضعناها في خلاط .. فأصبح لدينا ما يمكن
a carrot cake juice, and then that went into
وصفه بعصير فطيرة الجزر و من ثم
a balloon frozen in liquid nitrogen to create
وباستخدام بالون مجمد بسائل النتروجين
this hollow shell of carrot cake
استطعنا ان نصنع كرة من آيس كريم فطيرة الجزر
ice cream, I guess, and it comes off
كما أعتقد انه يمكن وصفها
looking like, you know,
وقد بدت كما تبدو هنا .. مثل
Jupiter's floating around your plate.
كوكب المشتري و هو يدور في فلك داخل صحن التقديم
So yeah, we're transforming things into
في الحقيقة نحن نغير الاطعمة
something that you have absolutely
الى نماذج حتماً
no reference for.
لم تمر عليكم من قبل
HC: And here's something we have no
هومارو كانتو : وهذا طبق لا مثيل
reference to eat. This is a cigar, and
له على الاطلاق .. هذه سجائر
basically it's a Cuban cigar made out of
في الاساس هي سيجار كوبي مصنوع
a Cuban pork sandwich, so we take these
من شطيرة لحم الخنزير الكوبية
spices that go into the pork shoulder,
واخذنا بعض التوابل و قطع من كتف لحم الخنزير
we fashion that into ash. We take
وشكلنا بواسطتها ما يشبه رماد السجائر
the sandwich and wrap it up in
واخذنا هذا السندويش و قمنا بلفه
a collard green, put an edible label
بورقة غلاف و علامة تجارية قابلة للأكل
that bears no similarity to
لكي يصبح لدينا طبق مطابق تماما
a Cohiba cigar label, and we put it
للسيجار الكوبي ذات الماركة " كوهيبا " وقدمناه
in a dollar ninety-nine ashtray and charge
في منفضة سجائر كلفتها دولار و 99 سنت
you about twenty bucks for it. (Laughter)
وقمنا ببيع الطبق لكم ب 20 دولار ( ضحك )
HC: Delicious.
هومارو كانتو : طبق لذيذ
BR: That's not it, though.
بين روشيه : ليس هذا فحسب
Instead of making foods that
فعوضاً عن أن نقوم بصناعة اطباق
look like things that you wouldn't eat,
تبدو كأشياء لن تأكلوها
we decided to make ingredients
قررنا ان نقوم بعمل مكونات
look like dishes that you know.
تشبه الاطباق التي تعرفونها
So this is a plate of nachos.
هذا هو طبق " الناشوز "
The difference between our nachos
ان الفرق بين الناشوز خاصتنا
and the other guy's nachos,
والناشوز الذي يقوم به الآخرون
is that this is actually a dessert.
هو أن هذا الطبق في الحقيقة هو طبق تحلاية
So the chips are candied,
ان الرقائق هنا هي رقائق مصنوعة من الحلوى
the ground beef is made from chocolate,
ولحم الضأن مصنوع من الشوكلاتة
and the cheese is made from a shredded
والجبنة مصنوعة من شراذم
mango sorbet that gets shredded
المانجا التي تم شرذمتها
into liquid nitrogen to look like cheese.
بواسطة النيتروجين السائل لكي تبدو كما الجبن
And after doing all of this
وبعد ان قمنا بهذه العمليات
dematerialization and reconfiguring
عملات اعادة التشكيل و التأهيل
of this, of these ingredients, we realized
لهذه المكونات .. أدركنا
that it was pretty cool,
انها أمرٌ ممتع
because as we served it, we learned that
لاننا عندما نقدمها لاحظنا
the dish actually behaves like the real thing,
ان الطبق يتصرف وكأنه الطبق الاصلي
where the cheese begins to melt.
فشرذمات الجبن كانت تذوب
So when you're looking at this thing
وعندما تنظر الى الطبق
in the dining room, you have this sensation
في المطعم تمتلك احساساً
that this is actually a plate of nachos,
انه طبق من الناشوز
and it's not really until you begin tasting it
ولكن ما ان تبدأ بتذوقه
that you realize this is a dessert, and
حتى تدرك أنه طبق تحلاية
it's just kind of like a mind-ripper.
ان الامر كالعبث بالفكر و الدماغ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
HC: So we had been creating
هومارو كانتو : لقد كنا نصنع
all of these dishes out of a
كل تلك الاطباق
kitchen that was more like
من مطبخنا الذي
a mechanic's shop than a kitchen, and
يبدو وكأنه محل ميكانيكي
the next logical step for us was to install
وكانت الخطوة المنطقية اللاحقة هي أن نعد
a state-of-the-art laboratory,
مختبر فني عام
and that's what we have here.
وهذا ما هو عليه الآن
So we put this in the basement, and we
فوضعنا هذا في القبو
got really serious about food, like
وأخذنا نأخذ الامر بجدية
serious experimentation.
فيما يخص القيام بالتجارب
BR: One of the really cool things about
بين روشيه : واحدة من اجمل الاشياء فيما يخص المختبر
the lab, besides that we have a new
غير وجوده المميز
science lab in the kitchen, is that,
- وجود مختبر علوم داخل مطبخ - هو
you know, with this new equipment, and
وجود هذه المعدات الجديدة
this new approach, all these
وهذه المقاربات الفكرية
different doors to creativity that we never
نحو ابواب الابداع التي ما كنا يوما نظن اننا سنطرقها
knew were there began to open, and so the
او نعلم كيفية فتحها
experiments and the food and the dishes
لذا فالتجارب و الاطعمة والاطباق
that we created, they just kept going
التي كنا نخترعها كانت تتزايد باستمرار
further and further out there.
يوماً بعد يوم من خارج ذلك المختبر
HC: Let's talk about flavor transformation,
هومارو كانتو : دعونا نتحدث عن تغير النكهات و تحويلها
and let's actually make some cool stuff.
ودعونا حقاً نصنع اموراً مميزة
You see a cow with its tongue hanging out.
هنا ترون بقرة تمد بلسانها
What I see is a cow about to eat something
ولكن ما أراه هو بقرة على وشك أكل شيء ما
delicious. What is that cow eating?
لذيذ . والسؤال ما الذي سوف تأكله البقرة ؟
And why is it delicious?
ولماذا هو لذيذ ؟
So the cow, basically, eats three basic
ان الأبقار في الاساس تأكل
things in their feed: corn, beets, and barley,
الذرة والفول والشعير
and so what I do is I actually
حسناً ما الذي أقوم به حقاً
challenge my staff with these crazy,
لكي أتحدى نفسي بهذه الامور الجنونية
wild ideas. Can we take what the cow
والافكار الجنونية .. هل بالإمكان أن اقوم بأخذ
eats, remove the cow, and then make
ما تأكله البقرة .. و ابعد صورة البقرة و من ثم
some hamburgers out of that?
اقوم بعمل " هامبرجر " من ذلك ؟
And basically the reaction tends to be
ومن المؤكد ان ردة الفعل على هذا
kind of like this. (Laughter)
سوف تكون من مثل هذه ( ضحك )
BR: Yeah, that's our chef de cuisine,
بين روشيه : هذا هو الشيف
Chris Jones. This is not the only guy
كريس جونز .. انه ليس الشخص الوحيد
that just flips out when we assign
الذي يأفأف حينما نطلب منه عملا ما
a ridiculous task, but a lot of these ideas,
أو مهمة سخيفة .. او الكثير من الافكار
they're hard to understand.
التي من الصعب استيعابها
They're hard to just get automatically.
ومن الصعب استيعابها مباشرة
There's a lot of research and a lot of
فهناك يجب ان تجري الكثير من الابحاث
failure, trial and error -- I guess, more error --
وسنفشل و سنجرب ونخطئ .. وربما نفشل اكثر
that goes into each and every dish,
وهذا نواجهه في عدة اطباق
so we don't always get it right, and it takes
لا نصيب دائماً و يحتاج الامر منا بعض الوقت
a while for us to be able to explain that
لكي نتمكن من تفسير ذلك
to people.
للناس
HC: So, after about a day of Chris and I
هومارو كانتو : بعد يوم قضيته انا وكريس
staring at each other, we came up with
ننظر في وجوه بعضنا .. استطعنا ان نصل لشيء
something that was pretty close
يشبه لحد ما
to the hamburger patty, and as you can
لحم الهمبرجر , كما ترون هنا
see it basically forms like hamburger meat.
انه مشكل تماما كما يشكل لحم الهمبرجر
This is made from three ingredients:
وهو مصنوع من 3 مكونات
beets, barley, corn, and so it
هي الذرة و الفول و الشعير
actually cooks up like hamburger meat,
ويتم طهيه كما يطهى لحم الهمبرجر
looks and tastes like hamburger meat,
ويبدو و نكهته تماما كما الهمبرجر
and not only that, but it's basically
وليس هذا فحسب .. لانه في الحقيقة
removing the cow from the equation.
هو ازالة البقرة من معادلة - صنع الهمبرجر -
So replicating food, taking it into that
واعادة تصنيع الطعام و التقدم الى
next level is where we're going.
المستوى الآخر .. وهذا ما نحن مقدمين عليه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
BR: And it's definitely the world's first
بين روشيه : وهو حتماً لحم الهمبرجر الاول
bleeding veggie burger,
الذي " يدمى " بعصارة الخضار
which is a cool side effect.
وهو من الأعراض الجانبية الممتعة
And a miracle berry, if you're not familiar
و توت يعتبر معجزة , ان لم تكونوا تعرفوه
with it, is a natural ingredient, and it
هو مكون اساسي ..
contains a special property.
وفي خصائص مميزة
It's a glycoprotein called miraculin,
حيث فيه بروتين سكري يدعى " كيراكولين "
a naturally occurring thing. It still freaks
وهو مكون طبيعياً .. ويصيبني بالفزع
me out every time I eat it, but it has a
في كل مرة استخدمه .. ولكن لديه
unique ability to mask certain taste
قدرة خاصة على تكوين مذاق معين - خداع نكهي -
receptors on your tongue, so that primarily
على مستقبلات النكهة في اللسان ..
sour taste receptors, so normally things
فحساسات النكهة الأساسية المتعلقة التي عادة تتذوق المرارة
that would taste very sour or tart,
تبدأ تبعاً لهذا الروتين السكري
somehow begin to taste very sweet.
بصورة ما تبدو حلوة المذاق
HC: You're about to eat a lemon,
هومارو كانتو : فإن كنت ستأكل الليمون ..
and now it tastes like lemonade.
فستشعر انها ليمونادا
Let's just stop and think about the
دعونا نتوقف ونفكر بهذا ..
economic benefits of something like that.
وبالمردود الاقتصادي عن أمر كهذا ..
We could eliminate sugar across the board
يمكننا ان نلغي السكر من الساحة
for all confectionary products and sodas,
من كل منتجات الحلويات و الصودا
and we can replace it with
وان نبدلها بهذه
all-natural fresh fruit.
الفاكهة الطبيعية النقية
BR: So you see us here cutting up
بين روشيه : كما ترون هنا عملية تقطيع
some watermelon. The idea with this
للبطيخ .. ان الفكرة من وراء هذا
is that we're going to eliminate tons of
هو التخفيف من أطنان " الاميال " الغذائية
food miles, wasted energy,
والطاقة المهدورة
and overfishing of tuna by creating tuna,
والصيد الجائر بزراعة سمك التونا
or any exotic produce or item
او اي منتج مميز
from a very far-away place,
من بقاع بعيدة عن أماكننا
with local, organic produce;
بواسطة تصنيع محلي و طبيعي
so we have a watermelon from Wisconsin.
هنا لدينا بطيخ من ويسكنسون
HC: So if miracle berries take sour things
هومارو كانتو : وان كان توت المعجزة يستطيع تحويل المرارة
and turn them into sweet things,
الى حلاوة
we have this other pixie dust
لدينا هذه الاحجية الأخرى
that we put on the watermelon, and it
التي نضع فيها البطيخ لكي نحوله
makes it go from sweet to savory.
من الحلاوة إلى اللذة
So after we do that, we put it into
بعد ان نقوم بذلك
a vacuum bag, add a little bit of seaweed,
نقوم بتفريغ الهواء منه ووضع القليل من بذور البحر
some spices, and we roll it, and this
وبعض البهارات و من ثم نلفها هكذا
starts taking on the appearance of tuna.
لكي تبدو كما التونا
So the key now is to make it
والهدف الان هو جعلها
behave like tuna.
تتفاعل و تتصرف كما التونا
BR: And then after a quick dip into some
بين روشيه : وبعد ان نقوم بغمسها بصورة سريعة
liquid nitrogen to get that perfect sear,
في نتروجين سائل للحصول على قوام مثالي
we really have something that looks,
يكون لدينا شيء يشبه و طعمة
tastes and behaves like the real thing.
تماما كما النسخة الاصلية منه - التونا -
HC: So the key thing to remember here is,
هومارو كانتو : الفكرة الاساسية التي يجب ان نتذكرها دوما
we don't really care
هو انه لا يهم
what this tuna really is.
ما هو مكون التونا
As long as it's good for you and good for
طالما انه مفيد و طعمه جيد و غير
the environment, it doesn't matter.
ضار للبيئة .. نعم الامر غير مهم
But where is this going?
ولكن إلى أين نصبوا بهذا ؟
How can we take this idea of tricking your
الى اين يمكننا ان نأخذ فكرة خداع
tastebuds and leapfrog it into something
مجسات التذوق و القفز بها الى الامام
that we can do today that could be
هل ما نقوم به اليوم
a disruptive food technology?
يمكن ان يكون تكنولوجيا غذائية هدامة ؟
So here's the next challenge.
حسناً اليكم التحدي التالي
I told the staff, let's just take a bunch
قلت لفريق العمل .. دعونا نأخذ
of wild plants, think of them as
حزمة من النباتات البرية
food ingredients. As long as they're
ونعاملها كمكونات غذائية .. طالما انها
non-poisonous to the human body,
غير مؤذية للجسم البشري
go out around Chicago sidewalks,
اذهبوا في انحاء شيكاغو
take it, blend it, cook it and then
اجمعوهم .. اخطلوهم .. ومن ثم اطبخوهم
have everybody flavor-trip on it at Moto.
ودعونا ندخل الزبائن في جولة من النكهات
Let's charge them a boatload of cash for this
ونأخذ منهم كماً كبيراً من المال لقاء هذا
and see what they think. (Laughter)
ولنرى ماذا يفكرون حيال هذا ( ضحك )
BR: Yeah, so you can imagine, a task
بين روشيه : نعم .. يمكنكم تخيل مهمة
like this -- this is another one of those
كهذه .. انها مهمة اخرى
assignments that the kitchen staff
فريق المطبخ كرهنا
hated us for. But we really had to almost
لاجلها .. ولكننا في الحقيقة وجراء هذا
relearn how to cook in general,
تعلمنا كيف نطبخ من جديد بصورة عامة
because these are ingredients, you know,
لان هذه المكونات .. كما تعلمون
plant life that we're, one, unfamiliar with,
القادم من عالم النبات لم نكن على دراية بها
and two, we have no reference for how
والامر الثاني اننا لم نكن نملك اي فكرة حيال
to cook these things because
طبخ هذه الامور
people don't eat them.
لان الناس لا تأكلها
So we really had to think about new, creative ways
لذا كان يتوجب علينا ان نأتي بأفكار جديدة و طرق ابداعية
to flavor, new ways to cook
فيما يخص النكهة و طرق جديدة في الطهي
and to change texture -- and that was
من اجل تغير المضمون وكان هذه المعضلة الاكبر
the main issue with this challenge.
في هذا التحدي
HC: So this is where we step into the future
هومارو كانتو : هذه هي الخطوة التي يجب ان ننطلق اليها في المستقبل
and we leapfrog ahead.
وان نقفز الى الامام نحوها
So developing nations
فالدول النامية
and first-world nations,
والدول المتقدمة
imagine if you could take these wild plants
ان تخيلنا انها تستطيع ان تستخدم النباتات الطبيعية
and consume them, food miles would
وتستهلكها يمكننا ان نوفر " الميلات " الغذائية
basically turn into food feet.
ونحولها الى " أثر " غذائي إيجابي
This disruptive mentality of what food is
ان الفكر " الخاطىء " لما هو الغذاء اليوم
would essentially open up the encyclopedia
يمكن ان يفتح موسوعة اساسية
of what raw ingredients are, even if we just
متعلقة بالمكونات الاساسية للأطعمة ان استطعنا فقط
swapped out, say, one of these for flour,
ان نبدل واحد فقط من الحبوب الاساسية - الطحين -
that would eliminate so much energy
من اجل ان نقلص استهلاك الطاقة
and so much waste.
والمخلفات
And to give you a simple example here as to
ولكي اعطيكم فكرة عن هذا
what we actually fed these customers,
وعن ما نقدمه للزبائن
there's a bale of hay there
لدينا قش
and some crab apples.
وبعض بقايا التفاح
And basically we took hay and crab apples
ونحن نأخذ القش و التفاح
and made barbecue sauce out of those two ingredients.
ونصنع منه صلصة بابركيو من هذين المطونين
People swore they were eating
والناس تأكلهما
barbecue sauce, and this is free food.
وتظن أنها صلصلة الباربكيو حقاً .. وهو طعام مجاني
BR: Thanks, guys.
بين روشيه : شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق )